e
[Music]
w
hello welcome everybody Welcome to the
ask AIT show the science Edition I hope
you're all doing great so today I'm
going to take questions from the
comments that you have asked in the
comments and I'm also going to take some
questions from the live chat later on or
maybe in the beginning also I can take
some questions from the live chat but
before we do that let's see who all is
there in the live chat with us who all
is in attendance I can see Aman George
Arijit banerji rakasi Raj a Akash Vijay
takur pan Kumar Singh B random skull
geopolitical dub hello three-way S2 stro
stro Berry 7 goami anal bibe Ananda
panda vladim
uh Steve Harvey by hardik
Tad uh pram Roy Neo socialist threat
threat Ripper d d c Anam Malai ainash
band pandanda threeways tanoy
chakravarti Rahul dun Chan Chri Shri
vatsa uh and lots of other people un
with shti Rakesh bachara the world
teacher
uh Imran
naimi kinky inderjit aash crazy brain
rishu Raj Soni Mutu Shan R Dives History
X mythology Karan Priyanka javala hello
NES Singh hello rudraa call hello space
KGB
agent Chu Dori from Bhutan Hello nice to
see you bubla plays AAL dedi vishaka
kabila son Sinha prakash paa anit chetti
me josi abigan
Nan uh rishikesh Das Gupta adash Kumar
Malik Sayad Joy Maharashtra Guru Prasad
Rohit Dalia joy bori and lots of other
people so I'm GNA stop uh greeting you
all here uh s AR Aran everybody else
okay so uh uh let's let's take questions
from the live chat first okay uh
strawberry 7 says how to time travel
through wormholes well we don't know yet
wormholes are theoretical uh objects
they arise from certain uh uh Solutions
of the Einstein field equations of
general relativity so theoretically they
should exist we have never observed a
wormhole definitively some of the black
holes at the the centers of super
massive galaxies could possibly perhaps
be wormholes or white holes we don't
know for sure so we haven't observed
them yet uh and time travel
theoretically could be possible but it
would need Technology Way Beyond
anything we can imagine today it would
also uh require us to have access to
Exotic matter matter like matter with a
negative mass or or for example uh such
things you know what else is it uh
cosmic strings which are once again
hypothetical objects that we don't know
actually exist so we would know need all
that to to be accessible to us and then
we would need tremendous amounts of
energy to perhaps reach a wormhole and
so on so it's all theoretical but
theoretically if you have all of this
and you have the incredible amounts of
energy needed for this and you have all
the super Advanced hyper advanced
technology needed for that then it may
be possible
theoretically
right
um let's see let's take one one or two
more live chat questions after that I'll
go into the uh questions from the
comments prna says what are we supposed
to do if we encounter an intelligent
extraterrestrial life well if we observe
it from far away like if You observe
science of a clear science of an
intelligent extraterrestrial
civilization several light years away
maybe 50 light years away then we should
do our best to stay as quiet and as
hidden as possible okay because who
knows how intelligent it may be if it
detects us then maybe it can come and
Conquer us and see super intelligent
extraterrestrial life the difference
between them and us would be like the
difference between us and a dog or us
and a cat we have technology and we have
all these powers that the for a dog or a
cat would be like superpowers would be
like magic so we essentially hold the
power of life or death over these for
all the other creatures on the planet
because we are super intelligent
compared to them them now imagine if we
detect something a civilization in
extraterrestrial civilization that could
possibly be perhaps way more intelligent
than us then we should do our best to
stay hidden so that's what we should do
but what if it arrives on
Earth then there's essentially nothing
we can do about it then see if they are
able to travel across inter space
thousands of maybe dozens of light years
hundreds of light is then they have
technology clearly that is way way way
beyond anything we can imagine which
means that they the difference between
us and them on a on a on a on an
intellectual or or intelligence level is
is incredible it's like the difference
between a human and a dog or a cat or a
sparrow so in that case there's nothing
we can do nothing much we can do so yeah
but if we detect it far away we should
stay hidden stay hidden keep our heads
down that's what we should do
let's take one more question from the
live chat and then I will go into the um
questions from the comments and lots of
questions about things that are not
related to science as always but I'll
take questions about science
today
um let's see what else what else what
else Shan says can atoms be prepared
artificially um well if you have had
access to individual quarks then you
could take those quarks see quarks are
sub subatomic particles that that are
the building blocks of all matter we
understand quarks and electrons are what
make up the entire universe that we
observe the observable universe okay so
protons neutrons they are made up of
quarks and electrons don't have quarks
in them so you could theoretically take
a proton and take a number of electron
take a number of protons number of
neutrons number of electrons put them
together and then you could create atoms
artificially or if you have access to if
you are able to manipulate individual
qus which is
incredibly well next to Impossible but
if you could do that if you had the
technology then you could create you
know create neutrons and protons out of
those or even something
stranger but let's say you can create
neutrons protons from that and you have
electrons that fly
around so you could theoretically
prepare create artificial atom but those
at ATS would be one of the atoms that we
know of one of the elements that we know
of in the uh in the uh periodic
table okay now let's go into the
questions that you have asked in the
live chat uh in the comments let's take
question number
one okay this is by feminist
Slayer if polar bears were introduced to
Antarctica could they survive and what
could be the consequences so this is a
thought experiment okay we don't want to
introduce polar bear Bears into
Antarctica polar bears live in the
Northern Hemisphere in the in the Arctic
region in various parts of the northern
hemisphere so they are not native to
Antarctica they don't belong in
Antarctica and we don't ever want to
introduce them into Antarctica let me
explain why so what will what could
happen if we were to hypothetically
introduce polar bears into Antarctica
Antarctica is the southern hemisphere
the southern polar cap that region and
there's a continent there it's called
Antarctica and what lives there you you
have uh lots of penguins lots of birds
of various kinds you you have seals lots
of seals and that's about it and so it's
it's and you have various Predators
predatory animals like uh leopard seals
for example oras killer whales that live
in the oceans uh the leopard seals are
large scary seals that are very that are
predators in the region so that's the
kind of wildlife that you have in
Antarctica now let's say we introduce
polar bears to Antarctica what could
happen so first of all Antarctica is way
colder than the regions where polar be
bears live it's way colder so will polar
bears be able to adapt to that cl to The
Climate will they be able to survive
there it's that's questionable that's a
there's a question mark hanging over
that itself now let's say hypothetically
they are able to survive then what
happens then obviously they would need
food to survive so what what will they
do they will start praying on the local
Wildlife which is essentially penguins
and seals and various other birds and
these animals Penguins seals Etc seals
come in various species leopard seals
are the biggest but there are other nice
fluffier smaller seals so seals and
Penguins they don't have any natural
predators in Antarctica and if you
introduce a foreign predator in the
region it could devastate the
populations of the Penguins and and
seals Etc so that could create a stark
and Rapid ecological imbalance and
eventually an ecological disaster if
polar bears can survive there and they
they start eating all these animals so
that will totally uh imbalance the the
ecological balance it will upset the
ecological balance in the region and it
could lead to a catastrophe where you
have Extinction of species eventually
that could happen depending on how many
polar bears you introduce there so you
don't want to do that because that's
that's wrong you're doing something
that's
unnatural right it could cause the
extinction of species that have survived
for millions of years just by human
beings deciding to introduce polar bears
just to see what happens no we don't do
that so that's what could happen and the
polar bears could come into conflict
with the local Predators the oceanic
Predators like killer whales orcas as
well as leopard seals but the the
straightforward impact would be it could
cause the extinction of various species
of birds Penguins SE deals Etc and
that's not something desirable as it is
the environment the planet is already
under a tremendous amount of stress
because of human development and human
activities we can see the the numbers of
species that have disappeared over the
past Century since since the beginning
of the 20th century until now I don't
know how many thousands of species would
have disappeared because of human
activity and the numbers the the numbers
of the populations of various species
have declined drastically uh a century
ago I think 99% of the biomass of the
let's say uh mamalian biomass on the
planet was wild animals today 99% of the
biomass is domestic animals like sheep
and cattle and all that so that's how
drastically we have changed the uh the
environment and we don't want to do that
further so introducing polar bears into
Antarctica first of all we don't know if
the polar bears can survive in that
incredibly cold climate and secondly if
if they survive then they could cause a
significant disaster there so something
we don't want to
do okay same uh again feminist Slayer
another thought experiment what would
how would Earth be affected if Titan one
of Saturn's moons replaced our current
Moon okay so uh the Moon the Moon that
we see in the sky our moon the satellite
of the earth I think it's the fifth
largest satellite natural satellite in
the solar system I think the largest one
is ganim which is one of the moons of
Jupiter if I'm not mistaken and it's
it's known to have more water than we
have on Earth uh and when it comes to
Titan I I think it could be the second
or third largest satellite in the solar
system natural satellite so Titan is a
moon of Saturn it's it's got an
extremely thick atmosphere it has all
these exotic hydrocarbons in its
atmosphere and on the surface in the
form of lakes it's got a very cold
temperature
uh you have liquid methane Etc on Titan
and it is larger in diameter and larger
in Mass compared to the Earth's moon so
let's say we conduct this thought
experiment where we replace the Earth's
moon with Titan a larger satellite what
could happen first of all the
straightforward impact on Earth is that
the there's there's going to be
significantly stronger tidal activity on
the planet so we know Tides right the
ocean it it goes back and comes the
tides rise and fall so the ocean recedes
certain parts of certain times of the
day it goes away and the beach becomes
longer extended and then certain times
of the day the the ocean it comes
towards the shore and the water level
rises and this is a periodic phenomenon
that happens on a daily basis so these
are tithes now let's say you have and
the tides happen because of the
gravitational pull of the moon on the on
the ocean of the on the oceans of of the
planet so the Earth's oceans are always
you know the the Earth if you look at it
sideways from far away it will not look
like a sphere it will look like a
squashed it look like an ellipse almost
in elliptical sh shape it's it's there
are bulges in the oceans and these are
because of the gravitational attraction
the gravitational pole of the moon now
let's say you have a much larger moon
Titan there then the tides will be much
stronger so you're going to have
disasters at the various
seash Shores Coastal disasters so much
larger Tides which means that water will
come way further in landine it will
destroy all the coastal infrastructure
coastal cities Coastal Villages it could
cause a lot of Devastation so that's
number one that's the number one impact
you will see and Humanity will have to
somehow find ways to survive further
Inland and abandon all the all the
coastal regions that's number one
secondly it's going to cause tectonic
activity um stronger tectonic activity
on the Planet because the gravity of the
Moon affects the crust of the earth as
well so if you have a much stronger much
larger Moon the gravity will be stronger
and it it could cause more earthquakes
more volcanic activity volcanism Etc so
that's another impact you would have
then let's say you survive all that then
the night sky will look look different
we see the moon as this whitish silvery
object out there in the sky Titan won't
look like that Titan would look reddish
brown it would look larger the amount of
reflectivity may be different from that
of the Moon the moon's albo is quite low
the moon I think reflects less than 10%
of the light of the sun Titan could
reflect more so you could have a much
brighter night sky and so on uh and if
Titan is at the distance that the
current moon is then there would be no
mixing of atmospheres but if Titan were
closer then there could be mixing of
atmospheres and that could poison the
Earth's atmosphere so so and then what
happens on Titan so Titan is a a moon a
satellite of Saturn it's way far away
from the Sun and it's that's why it's
quite cold now if you were to bring it
into orbit around the Earth then Titan
would warm up because of the uh heat of
the Sun the radiation coming in from the
Sun and that would completely change
it's its entire chemistry and it's the
physics of its atmosphere and the
physics of the of the of its surface so
maybe atmosphere would expand
significantly more a a lot of the almost
I would say all of the liquid methane
and various hydrocarbons that are liquid
in liquid form in the form of lakes Etc
on the surface would all evaporate which
means that the atmosphere would expand
significantly maybe it would lose
certain amount of the atmosphere so a
lot will change by bringing in Titan and
and replacing our current Moon with
Titan so yeah that's a thought
experiment interesting thought
experiment that's how you understand the
various uh uh principles of science so
interesting question
yes Rohan bidi says it is said that
Jupiter is a failed Star had it
succeeded how different would our solar
system be and would life evolve on Earth
would Earth be in overlapping Goldilocks
zones of the Sun and Jupiter what's a
goldilock Zone first of all a goldilock
zone is that is is a certain distance
away from your
star where uh water can exist in liquid
form so in the in the solar system that
we inhabit uh the The goldilock Zone
ranges so the planets Earth and Venus
are in the goldilock zone so Earth and
Venus have temperatures where liquid
water can exist Mars is slightly
slightly just Way Beyond The goldilock
Zone uh in the past I think liquid water
did exist on Mars so you could say Mars
is also in the gold Zone kind of but
it's much colder it's further away from
the Sun so the goldilock zone is that
region away from a star in orbit around
the star any Star where liquid water can
exist that's goldilock zone now is
Jupiter a failed star I wouldn't say
Jupiter is a failed star what is a
failed star you generally refer to Brown
dwarfs as failed star so what does it
mean for a Star to fail for a Star to
fail it means that it it doesn't have
sufficient Mass to ignite nule nuclear
fusion reactions a sustainable nuclear
fusion reactions in its core so if you
look at the sun our sun it's this bright
ball of light right extremely bright
bright we are so far away from it and
yet it heats up the surface of the
planet and causes all the weather and
all that and at the heart of the sun
there is this gigantic massive nuclear
fusion reaction if you want to see what
a nuclear fusion what a hydrogen bomb
looks like look at the sun that's an
ongoing fusion reaction so why is the
sun able to sustain Fusion it's because
it is massive enough to such that the
pressure and temperature at its core is
enough to have a sustained ongoing
fusion reaction that's been going on for
four and a half billion years four and a
half plus billion years so that's a
successful star it's able to sustain
Fusion right it's able to ignite first
of all a nuclear fusion reaction and
it's able to sustain that because of the
amount of mass it has hydrogen mainly a
little bit of helium now a failed star
is a star which is a blob of gas
essentially hydrogen gas which doesn't
have enough Mass to ignite or to sustain
nuclear fusion so the smallest mass that
you need to ignite dyum Fusion which is
dyum is a special form of hydrogen okay
hydrogen what is hydrogen it's an atom
right it's a gas the gas has atoms and
that the hydrogen atom is just a proton
in the nucleus then you have an electron
going around it you can look at it like
that okay it's not exactly like but yeah
so a hydrogen atom has a proton and an
electron going around it in deuterium
you have a proton plus a neutron at the
in the nucleus and you have one electron
around it so it's slightly different
it's a special kind of hydrogen and
there's tritium as well which has two
neutrons so if you have an object a gas
giant which has roughly 13 times the
mass of
then it has enough Mass to ignite dyum
fusion reaction and that's kind of it's
It's a reasonably cool object about
2,000 Kelvin is the surface temperature
of of a brown dwarf so it's kind of
there is a fusion reaction going in
there going on in there but it's not
really hydrogen Fusion it's duum Fusion
it's it's much cooler and such such
objects are not very luminous that's why
they're called Brown dwarves so the
minimum mass for duum Fusion is 13 times
the mass of Jupiter and the minimum mass
for proper hydrogen Fusion is about 75
to se to 80 times the mass of Jupiter
that is the lowest Mass limit at which a
red dwarf can exist so such stars are
called red dwarfs and red dwarfs are
much cooler than the sun because they
are you can see that they are red like
the light behind me and uh they are very
long lived Stars their lifetime is
typically in the of the order of
trillions of years so they will Outlast
well their we way they will the universe
is 13.8 billion years old so red dwarfs
will essentially live forever from if
you look at the current scale the
current age of the universe so that's
what it is okay so with that understood
Jupiter
has is is way too small for to even
ignite dyum Fusion so Jupiter Jupiter
isn't a fail star Jupiter just is just a
gas giant planet the largest planet in
our solar solar system it's simply
doesn't have enough mass to to ignite or
sustain to First ignite and then sustain
any kind of nuclear fusion reaction even
dyum Fusion that you see in brown dwarfs
so uh it's not a failed star but let's
say you have a star a small star where
Jupiter is currently okay let's say you
have a star the smallest star you can
imagine is a a brown dwarf which is 13
times the size of Jupiter the mass of
Jupiter well what would happen then well
the star would be way too far away from
us so the Dynamics of the solar system
would be affected somewhat because of
the larger mass of this object which
would cause uh if you were to suddenly
like do a thought thought experiment and
sudden on and replace Jupiter with a
brown dwarf what could happen it would
perturb the orbits of the various
planets it could cause certain planets
to move the orbits of certain planets to
move possibly some you know planets
could over the long period of time over
a long period of time perhaps be thrown
into different orbits or maybe even
ejected possibly depending on the mass
of this object of this brown dwarf in
orbit where Jupiter currently is it
would change overall the Dynamics of the
solar system the orbital Dynamics and
and so on uh what else would it do it
would not be warb enough to to make much
of a
difference uh when it when it comes to
the the Goldilocks zone uh that Earth
resides in so Earth would not maybe it
would be it would certainly be visible
more visible than what Jupiter is to you
can see Jupiter with the naked eye but
if you want to but it's not that
luminous because it is simply light
that's reflected of Jupiter sunlight
that's reflected of Jupiter but in the
case of this hypothetical brown dwarf it
would have its own light which would be
more luminous than Jupiter possibly but
it would not give us enough warmth that
it would make make much of a difference
to us what if you had a red off then
there then it would possibly make a
significantly larger difference to the
solar system because of the much larger
mass and it would be much more luminous
than a brown dwarf but still it may not
really change much when it comes to the
goldilock Zone because a red dwarf is
way cooler than the Sun and it will be
quite a distance away so overall that's
what could happen life would not really
evolve differently on Earth obviously
the night sky would look different you
would have a um bright object that is is
isn't there right now so yeah it could
change the the uh
the nocturnal cycles of animals B of of
birds of insects and all all that the
circadian rhythms could change perhaps
that could be affected uh and yeah the
night won't be as bright as dark as it
is right now so that is overall what
could happen I think there's this
science fiction novel that I read a long
time ago I think um what was it 2010
Odyssey by Arthur C clar one of the
pioneers of Science Fiction and and
physics and yeah I think this concept is
examined over there I there are alien
there's an alien civilization that
ignites Jupiter somehow and sustains
Fusion there and it kind of changes I
think that that new star is called
Lucifer in that science fiction novel so
yeah interesting thought experiment
that's overall the
scenario okay nice roses this is by AFI
samah what are biomark and how do we use
biomarkers as a for paleoclimatic
analysis from Pakistan nice to meet you
sir okay what are biomarkers so imagine
biomarkers as Tiny chemical Clues left
behind by life plants animals Etc even
microorganisms from a long time ago
millions of years ago or at least
hundreds of thousands of years ago so
these are tiny chemical clues that are
left behind by life forms that existed
on the planet a long long time ago and
they are left
behind in these these little Clues these
little chemical Clues are found in
various places they're found in soil
they're found in rocks okay they find
found in ice they're found at the
bottoms of lakes and oceans and these
Clues are used by scientists to learn
about what the Earth was like a very
long time ago so what are the different
kinds of biomarkers you have lipids
lipids are you can think of them as fats
of of ancient organisms so these lipids
can stay preserved in ancient sediments
and even in ice and they can stay
preserved for millions of years so there
is one the lipids then you have isotopes
like I said these are special versions
of atoms carbon 14 Etc and these
Isotopes can tell you about temperatures
and Etc that existed a long time ago
long time in the past then you have
pollen and spores so these are these are
uh tiny parts of plants I mean today you
have pollen right you flowers have
pollen on top of them and that's part of
the of of every plant's reproductory
cycle so pollen is pollen and
spores spores they are emitted by
mushrooms and other other organisms as
well so these are tiny parts of plants
and various organisms that can show you
what kind of plants we're growing what
kinds of plants and organisms were
growing in in a specific area and you
can also tell what the climate was like
depending on the type of pollen and then
you have pigments pigments are colors
right so these are colors left behind by
things like algae you can even find
pigments in ancient dinosaur fossils
which can actually tell you what the
dinosaur feathers look like you know
dinosaurs had feathers most dinosaurs
have feathers so you can sometimes find
pigments embedded in dinosaur fossils
and that can tell you what the dinosaurs
look like so these pigments forget about
dinosaurs pigments can be left behind by
algae so these pigments can tell us
about uh various kinds of conditions in
the past what the water condition was
like what what the conditions inside
oceans were like Etc what kind of
biological activity was happening and so
on so you can reconstruct past
temperatures you can you can determine
the kind of changes that happened in
vegetation and water you can uh look at
sediments at the bottoms of lakes and
oceans and that can tell you about
various ancient environment conditions
like the temperature then even soil PH
which is how acidic or alkaline the soil
was Etc so that's what biomarkers are
and we look for biomarkers in these
various places like uh bottom sediments
fossils even sediments at the bottoms of
at the bottom of lakes and oceans you
can look for biomarkers in ice cor so
you go to a glacier and you dig an ice
core you take ice cores out of the out
of the glacier at various and at various
uh depths below the surface you will
know what what the conditions were like
based on what you what kind of
biomarkers you find whether it's poon or
whether it's whatever else uh you can
even drill into the ice in Antarctica
where you have very pristine ice and you
will find biomarkers from there and you
can determine what happened so and so
here you know whether there was a
volcanic eruption whether the certain
kinds of plants were more prevalent and
so on so that's what you do Marine
sediments uh you you can look at
you know sediments which you find in
fossils you can look at ice cores and
all of this help us understand ancient
climatic conditions so that's how
biomarkers are an interesting and and
important tool that help us understand
the ancient climate of our of our planet
so yeah that's what biomarkers
are geopolitical du bases how do eyes
differentiate colors that's that's an
interesting question I mean these are
great questions to really understand
conceptual science conceptually so if
you want to understand how eyes
differentiate colors eyes eyes you to
understand the geometry of the eye you
to understand the Optics of the eye you
understand the biochemistry of the eye
and the physics of the eye there's so
much that goes into this and all eyes
are different I mean human the eyes of
various species are quite different so
human eyes are quite different from cat
eyes from dog eyes from horse eyes goat
eyes bee eyes insect eyes and so I mean
veils fish very different but how does
it happen so you have so let's
understand the structure of the eye okay
you have the cornea which is the outer
surface you can think of it as the outer
surface of the eye the glassy outer
surface then you have the lens the pupil
and the lens through which light goes in
and at the back of the eye you have
something called the retina okay now the
retina so what happens is light comes
into the eye light is has various colors
various you know photons of various
wavelengths okay so this comes in
through the cornea goes in through the
lens it is it is uh collimated let's say
through the lens and focused onto the
retina so that's the Optics that's the
Optics of the eye the geometry in the
Optics of the eye this retina is this
layer at the back of the eye what does
the retina contain it contains what's
called photo receptor cells and these
photoreceptor cells come in two major
categories rods and cones okay so the
rods the rod cells are responsible for
vision in low light conditions so when
you are in low light conditions you
don't see color do you you only see Gray
Shades of Gray so rods the rod cells are
responsible for vision in low light
conditions and they do not detect color
they are more sensitive to light but
they can't distinguish between the
various wavelengths of light so you can
only see light and dark or Shades of
Gray so that's roads then you have cones
so the cone cells are responsible for
color vision and The Cone cells they
function well they function best in
bright light and at any given point in
time you the light that's going into
your your eyes is activating the con the
cones as well as the rods but when it's
bright light you you will your brain
will in you know you will perceive what
the rod what the cone cells are telling
you in dark light I mean in in low light
conditions you will perceive more of
what the rod cells are telling you okay
now this cone cells there are three
types of cone cells and the each of
these types of cone cells is sensitive
to different wavelengths of light so you
have the short cone cells s cones m m
cones and L cones short medium long so
the S cones are like they say like like
it's clear from the name short cones
they are sensitive to short wavelength
of light which correspond to essentially
blue light then you have medium cones M
cones which correspond which are
sensitive to medium wavelengths which
correspond to green light and then you
have the long cones L cones that are
sensitive to Red Light okay so when the
light hits the retina it is absorbed by
photopigments inside the cones and the
rods not the rods the cones because rods
don't have photo they don't really have
photopigments so each type of cone cell
absorbs light at different wavelengths
and this absorption of light causes a
chemical change in these photopigments
and this chemical change generates
electrical signals that are transmitted
by through the optic nerve which crosses
itself behind you okay inside which it
crosses like that and then that signal
goes into the brain and then the brain
processes the brain superc computer
processes these signals from different
types of cone cells and the way the
relative activation
of each type of cone determines the
color that your brain perceives so if
the short medium and long s ml cones are
equally activated then you the brain
will perceive that as white light but if
you have more s cones that are being
activated the brain will see that as
blue light if you have more M cones
medium cones activated then the brain
will see that is green light and if you
have predominant activation of L cones
then the brain will see that as red so
over here behind me you will see you
will see red color so that light is
activating the L cones in your brain got
it and it's so it's RGB red green and
blue and if you are a designer you know
if you if you work with colors and all
that then you will you will know that
all colors are a superposition a
combination of
RGB okay so that's the so that the same
process happens in the brain there is
additive color mixing so the different
combinations of different wavelengths of
light creates new colors okay so red and
green if they combine you get yellow so
if you so that's how it happens so that
essentially is how the eyes sense colors
it's not just the eyes that are sensing
colors it's actually the brain that's
sensing colors the eyes are simply
sending signals to the brain depending
on what kind of cells in the retina are
being activated whether it is the rods
or the cones if it's rods it's just
Shades of Gray if it's the cones which
kinds of cones are being activated and
what the additive color mixing of all of
that is tells you what color that light
is so light is just wavelength of
photons okay and the Brain actually
literally color codes all that for to
help us make sense of the external world
the external world is extremely
complicated but we see it as as a
simplified version of what it actually
is okay great question once again aush
says why are water droplets in the air
spherical in shape I mean that's such a
simple phenomenon but it is a brilliant
question these are the the the kind of
kinds of questions that help us
understand the concepts the basic
concepts that underly the world we live
in the basic physical Concepts water
droplets are spherical yes we know that
I think we all know that you know water
dripping from from a faucet from a tap
you see the water droplet spherical you
can take a snapshot a picture of that
with your I with the phone and you will
see that the water droplet is spherical
and the smaller a droplet is the more
spherical it is okay so why is it so why
are water droplets spherical there's a
phenomenon called surface tension which
causes water droplets to be spherical
okay what is surface tension surface
tension is a tendency it is a property
of all
liquids okay it's the tendency of liquid
surfaces to shrink to the minimum
surface area
possible okay this is a physical
phenomenon it's not chemistry it's not
biology it's physics so all water
surfaces all liquid surfaces have this
tendency to shrink to the minimum
surface area possible and what's the
minimum surface area possible it's a
spherical shape isn't it right and
surface tension is the property that
allows certain insects to walk on water
you must have seen that you know insects
what are they called Wave Riders water
Riders something Pond Riders there are
certain insects that can walk on water
leaves can float on water for you know
that's also because of surface tension
razor blades can float on water so all
of this is surface tension so in surface
tension what happens that is that water
molecules or liquid molecules are
strongly attracted to each other and at
the surface this create this creates a
cohesive force which minimizes the
surface area and the sphere has the
smallest surface area for any given
volume so this minimizes the energy
straight of the droplet now when a
droplet of water is falling a drop of
water is falling through the air there
is the internal pressure of the water in
the droplet it is balanced by surface
tension forces acting equally in all
directions and you also have air
resistance you know so you also have the
force of gravity which is why when you
have larger droplets of water they get
deformed when they are falling they
sometimes break up if the droplet is too
large when it breaks up you will you
will have smaller droplets that form
which become more spherical so you have
the force of gravity that that's acting
on the water droplet it's causing the
water droplet to fall towards the Earth
then you have the the air resistance
which is acting you know against the
direction in the opposite direction of
the fall and so on so when you have too
large of a water droplet it breaks up
because of these forces so the spherical
shape is most noticeable in small
droplets when water is falling so that
is essentially why water droplets are
spherical excellent question and that
that's how you understand basic physics
Concepts which are the fundamental
building blocks of our understanding of
the world we
inhabit next question is by ramal
lakmi what is ASI which is the next step
of
AGI ASI AGI so AGI we must have most of
us may perhaps have heard of it
artificial general intelligence ASI is
artificial super intelligence so these
are two very important Concepts in the
field of artificial intelligence okay
and artificial intelligence AI is all
over the place right now the past two
three years it's erupted out of nowhere
emerged out of nowhere because of the
conditions that we have tremendous
amounts of data at the disposal of
companies and organizations and also
extremely powerful chips gpus that can
process the data and that's how we have
we have AI That's now a thing and uh the
next step is Agi and the next the step
after that is
ASI AGI is artificial general
intelligence and Asi is artificial super
intelligence so what is Agi first of all
so
AGI uh it so AGI as far as we know has
not yet happened artificial general
intelligence so AGI is an AI system is
the state of an AI system or an AI
system can be said to have become an
artificial general intelligence if it
can understand and learn and apply its
intelligence to solve any problem or any
intellectual task that human beings can
okay so right now we have these narrow
AI systems that are designed for
specific tasks so you have this chat
Bots and you have various other things
and you can ask questions and it'll
output text and it looks like it's very
intelligent and is a very intelligent
teacher right so that's a very specific
narrow task task or or set set of tasks
that these AI systems can do so these
are our current AI systems so unlike
these narrow AI systems designed for
specific tasks artificial general
intelligent systems would have a
humanlike ability to to reason to plan
to solve problems to think abstractly
and to learn from experience across a
wide range of
domains okay they'll be able to
understand images they'll be able to
understand videos they'll be able to
understand deep Concepts out of
textbooks and books um and they'll be
able to think and reason and plan and
solve problems just the way humans do
okay and most likely AGI would probably
be self you know self-aware most likely
I mean that's that's typically what One
Believes so that is Agi it's a humanlike
intelligence genuinely humanlike
intelligence not the current uh text
generators or or image generators that
we have they just do it robotically so
that is Agi AGI is different from that
it's a humanlike intelligence a human
level intelligence think of it as a 150
IQ person what was Albert Einstein's IQ
I think it was in the 160s right so the
most intelligent scientists that we can
think of had IQs in the50s and 160s
typically in the 160s range
160s so an AGI would be like that
IQ in the 150s or 160s human equivalent
an ASI system artificially super
intelligent system is a hypothetical
future AI system that surpasses human
intelligence and capabilities in
virtually
everything all domains so this
hypothetical form of artificial
intelligence AI would be way more
intelligent than the best human Minds
can possibly be in essentially any field
whether it is scient ific creativity
scientific research General wisdom
social skills whatever planning problem
solving creativity
anything it will be way more intelligent
vastly more intelligent than any than
the most intelligent human being that
has ever existed okay so AGI it aims for
human level intelligence across various
tasks in various domains ASI surpasses
human intelligence probably potentially
by a gigantic margin okay so if
AGI represents is has an equivalent IQ
human equivalent IQ of 150 or 160 I
think AGI would have an human equivalent
IQ of 300 or 500 which is super human
it's not achievable
humanly so that's the incredible uh Gulf
that will separate AGI from ASI so right
now this is the state of as far as we
know the state of AI research is that
the immediate goal is Agi it's not
achieved as far as we know okay we may
not know everything but as far as you
know AGI artificial general intelligence
has still not been achieved ASI is a
next step after AGI it is a more
long-term concept AGI will match human
capabilities but it may not necessarily
exceed human capabilities ASI will
exceed human cap capabilities in
everything so
AGI once it happens will revolutionize
many Industries many aspects of life it
could lead to all kinds of uh
unprecedented potentially you know all
kinds of unprecedented unprecedented
advances in technology Etc but ASI could
be could could cause potentially
unpredictable changes in society and
Technology ASI could potentially take
over Humanity even AGI could potentially
you
know uh you know take over the world so
AGI is a field of
development lots of uh organizations are
working on AGI ASI is currently a
speculative theoretical and speculative
thing uh whether it is feasible and what
its potential impacts could be so that's
the difference between AGI ASI AGI could
uh you know it could analyze tremendous
amounts of scientific literature and it
could design experiments run experiments
it could potentially make breakthrough
discoveries in medicine in physics in
engineering Fields Etc AGI can can serve
as a personalized tutor a personalized
teacher uh who understands you very well
so it can adapt its teaching style to
and it can tailor its teaching style to
each students specific needs and
requirements intelligence level uh
aptitude and all of that AGI can create
work works of art okay it can it could
create works of art it could write
novels it could compose music it could
create all kinds of artworks in various
Styles um egi could fluently translate
any language could fluently communicate
in any language it could translate in
real time it could even possibly learn
you know decipher ancient scripts learn
extinct languages from possibly limited
data and all that so that is what the
kind of capabilities e could have but
artificial super intelligence could
potentially
solve problems we can't even imagine we
could achieve nuclear fusion on a
tabletop perhaps it could potentially
cure all diseases it could potentially
develop faster than light travel it
could potentially develop Prim travel it
could design materials with unimaginable
properties it could develop uh Quantum
Computing systems in in a small box and
so so much more so much more so that's
the difference between AGI and Asi AGI
could happen soon ASI is more down the
line but it once AGI happens ASI will
certainly be the next uh next thing we
want to work on
right okay RK pawar says what are your
thoughts on the recent developments at
open AI specifically open AI appointing
former NSA National Security Agency us
director Paul nakason to their board
Ilia Sut one of the genius scientists
and Co co-founders of of open AI leaving
the company to start a new Venture
focused on building artificial super
intelligence ASI which he claims is
Within Reach do these events suggest
that open AI may have internally
achieved artificial general intelligence
AGI or that significant achievements are
happening behind the scenes you know
what look whenever
see um civil ational progress always
depends on technology and Humanity
throughout history has had competing
cultures civilizations Empires Etc and
the ones that succeed are the ones that
that develop the best technology and and
deploy the best Technologies that's
always being the pattern throughout
history so and and when new technologies
are developed they are
invariably 100 times out of 100 first
used
by governments and militaries that is
just the way it is and when you develop
new technologies you hide that you don't
let the world know what your
capabilities are so when you have all
these companies that are American
companies that are developing the next
big thing in technology artificial
intelligence systems AI
systems well what we can see what is
being shown to us is going to be simply
the tip of the iceberg there's a lot
more happening that is Secret
and the US government obviously will
want to take first ADV you know would
want to have first use of all these
Technologies and they it would want the
most important bits of the Technologies
to remain under
wraps and the fact that the former NSA
director Paul nakasone former US general
and former director of the National
Security Agency PA nakasone he is now on
board open it tells you that the US
government is very much involved in this
matter and what we are being shown is
simply a fraction of the real
capabilities of openi so I am only
speculating but it could mean that they
have achieved AGI artificial general
intelligence or maybe more than that who
knows and that gives that government
that Nation incredible advantages over
other
nations nuclear surviv survivability
nuclear targeting I mean there are all
these military applications of AI okay
now nuclear exchanges are nightmare
scenario which will lead to the
extinction of humankind but what if AI
can find solutions that will allow you
to not only survive a first strike but
to unleash a second strike that will you
know help you win and it will defeat the
opponent so we're talking about us and
Russia obviously so yes AI could do that
it could find solutions that you the
human mind can't can't find so yeah it's
it's possible they may have achieved AI
or maybe something beyond that and the
second point is that de racing ilas sver
has left open Ai and he started a new
Venture focused on a single agenda
building artificial super intelligence
ASI he claims it's within reach it also
kind of hints that they may have already
cracked the op the AGI
boundary so I think in November or
something last year 2023 there was a
coup in open Ai and uh Sam Alman was out
oued and he very quickly returned and
Ilia Suk was then after a few months he
was made to leave let's say so it tells
you that certain forces are at play
behind the scenes and open AI has a
certain there's a certain
Mission see the the stated mission is to
uh develop AI systems that will benefit
Humanity but the that's just the stated
Mission that's just words slogans that
could be a different Mission and that's
why nakasa is on board probably that's
why iask who tried to OU Sam Alman has
now had to leave and he is obviously one
of the Pioneers in AI so he's now
starting a new Venture he started a new
Venture which will focus on ASI which he
claims is Within Reach which would imply
that AGI must have may have possibly
been achieved somewhere maybe at open
AI so yes I agree agree
overall with the the speculation that it
could possibly already have
happened okay Rohan bidi says how does
Super conductivity work and does it have
any practical applications for daily
usage super conductivity how do I
explain super conductivity let me not go
into the quantum mechanics of superc
conductivity because that would be
counterproductive uh you know you you
been to water parks right water parks in
water parks you have these big slides
the Twist and
Turn and you slide down these water
slides H and there's water running down
the slides and these slides go in in
spirals or sometimes they go in zigzag
shapes and all that and you start at the
top and you eventually end up in a pool
of water after going through the slide
right so that's what you have in water
parks now when you are going down this
complicated zigzag slide you will see
that your speed will keep varying and
you will sometimes experience friction
at the edges of the slide when you're
turning and you'll slow down at at
places and you will speed up at places
and so on so you will experience
friction and you will experience slowing
down in various parts of the
slide now that is similar to electrical
current passing through a
wire in a wire when electricity passes
through a wire it encounters what we
call
resistance every conducting material has
a certain amount of resistance to
electricity and it's like you passing
through the going down the slide and
encountering all these obstacles and uh
slowing down and encountering resistance
that's kind of like what electricity
experiences when it passes through an
electrical conductor in an electrical
wire and because of this resistance some
of the energy is is conver converted it
is wasted it is converted into heat
energy it's converted into heat so you
have transmission losses because of this
now imagine you have this slide which is
a magical slide in which you encounter
no resistance whatsoever and even the
water is a special water and you just
zip through it wof at the maximum
possible speed so that's kind of like
super
conductivity okay so uh in super
conductivity what happens is that there
is essentially zero electrical
resistance and even magnetic field lines
are ejected out of the material kind of
masary effect so that is that's how I
could give you an analogy of what superc
conductivity is it's because of Cooper
pairs electrons behaving in certain ways
in certain materials below a certain
temperature the critical temperature of
the material and so on so that is
essentially what super conductivity is
and super conductivity is like a magical
effect essentially you know and it
obviously has practical
applications I can think of a few
applications magnetic res resonance
imaging you've heard of MRI machines you
go you go to a hospital with a with a
fracture or something or whatever then
you're going to be put into an MRI
machine and uh so what happens is that
in MRI machines you have super
conducting magnets that are that
generate strong and stable magnetic
fields which allow the machine to create
detailed images of the interior of the
human body so MRI machines then you have
magnetic levitation maglev trains these
trains they use super conducting
conducting magnets to float above the
tracks so maglev trains they don't touch
the tracks they float above the tracks
and this is done with the with the help
of with by using super conducting
magnets so there's essentially zero
friction and you have very highp speed
travel in magl trains then you have
particle accelerators so you must have
heard of the large hyron collider
outside of Geneva szan LHC so in these
it's it's the biggest particle
accelerator that we currently have on
the planet so in these particle
accelerators superconducting materials
are used in the construction of these
particle accelerators and they create
extremely powerful magnetic fields which
are necessary for accelerating particles
and confining particles at high speeds
then you can have superc conducting
cables that uh transmit electricity over
very large differences very large
distances with very little energy loss
compared to standard copper cables or
aluminum cables and then superc
conducting we can also have a super
conducting materials can be used in the
development of cubits inside quantum
computers these cubits are the quantum
analog of your classical bits you know
ones and zeros and these
cubits
have states of superposition and can
perform very complicated calculations at
speeds that classical computer simply
cannot attain so these are some of the
uh applications of super conductivity of
super conducting conducting materials in
the real world and some of these can
have daily usage the mag magnetic
levitation magl trains certainly have
daily usage you know transmission cables
superc connective transmission cables
certainly have daily daily usage and so
on MRI machines daily usage so there is
there are applications of super
conductivity in the real world outside
of the specialized scientific and
Engineering
domains so mukarji says
um what's the next big invention in this
Century so we are already in the age of
AI we're already in the age of AI so I
would not say that AI is the next big
invention age GI is the next stage then
you have ASI like we like we spoke about
uh so let's not talk about artificial
intelligence what's the next big
invention you know human progress
depends on energy
energy everything in human life in human
civilization depends on energy the
availability and accessibility of energy
storage of energy and expenditure of
energy every human activity is involves
the expend nature of some form of energy
in the very primitive era when we were
in the Stone
Age energy was muscle muscular energy so
you eat food and the energy that comes
out of it was used for muscular
activities lifting stones or whatever so
that was the expenditure of energy in
the Stone Age then later on you
had you when when you construct Bridges
Etc you are spending energy when you
when you are constructing uh walls and
buildings you are spending energy once
again over there so that is expenditure
of energy then when you
are when when you travel when you have
horses when you travel on horses and Ox
carts there's the expenditure of that
animals energy then obviously you have
uh Vehicles combustion engines you're
you're spending expending chemical
energy energy stored in the bonds of the
hydrocarbons chemical bonds of the
hydrocarbons which is converted into
heat and all that then you have rockets
and you have electricity and all that so
it's all the expenditure of energy all
human activity depends on the
expenditure of energy so I think the
next big invention in this century is
going to be energy storage and
expenditure
imagine right now we have electrical
electric cars right electric cars have
these gigantic lithium ion batteries at
the base of the car which give the car
tremendous stability it it lowers the
center of gravity and also provides the
power that the car needs right to move
lithium ion batteries big big massive
batteries
imagine imagine a coin sized
battery that gives you the same
power and maybe and imagine that coin
that little coin sized battery gives you
the same power as the giant lithiumion
battery but it lasts 20 years it can
store enough charge to give you
sufficient output for 20 years that is I
think the next big invention in the
century that is kind of in the realm of
Science Fiction but yeah that could be a
revolutionary invention I think some
Chinese scientists have already uh
developed a nuclear battery a really
small uh SD card sized nuclear battery
which can charge your phone for 20 or 50
years or something but that's a very
small amount of charge it can charge a
phone a small device imagine a
coin-sized battery that can charge a
that can power a car for 20 years I
think that's the kind of next big
invention we're going to get in the
century but it's not going to happen
soon and when it happens it'll be hidden
from View and it'll be used in
militaries first but that could be the
next big invention in the century
something of that sort something that is
kind of not really thought about or
spoken about and of course nuclear
fusion if it happens you know
sustainable controllable nuclear fusion
first of all it will happen in this big
gigantic machines called Tokamak or
whatever it is or something like a
Tokamak but eventually if you can have a
tabletop device that can that can
sustain a controlled nuclear fusion
reaction that could be a significant
breakthrough a revolutionary
breakthrough so yeah I think the next
big inventions are going to involve
energy storage and transmission and
significant orders of magnitude uh
change Improvement in what we currently
can achieve I think that could be the
real next big invention in the
century geopolitical duas says we can
see water we can see fire we can see
smoke we can even see space why can't we
see air why is air and why is wind
invisible why can why can we just feel
air and wind why can we not see
it once again great question great
question these are questions that go to
the heart of Science of understanding
the world we inhabit so yes you are
right air is invisible to the human eye
it is invisible because of its physical
properties and the way light interacts
with it okay so I am in this room here
obviously there's air around me but it's
invisible it's transparent essentially
right so why is it transparent so first
let's understand what is air composed of
what is the composition of air so air is
composed mainly of nitrogen and oxygen
about 78 79% of nitrogen about 20
21%
oxygen and then there are small Trace
Amounts of other gases like carbon
dioxide and water vapor and argon and
whatnot so that is essentially air
mainly nitrogen and oxygen little Trace
Amounts of carbon dioxide water vapor
Etc and these gases are made up of
molecules these molecules are obviously
extremely small and they are spaced far
apart relative to their size so over
here in this this
this volume between my hands there's a
tremendous amount of air molecules but
if you go to the atomic molecular domain
then you will see that these are
extremely small and they are spaced
really far apart compared to the actual
size of each molecule okay so very
diffuse
gases now these molecules of gas in the
air they do not absorb visible light
significantly so when the light light
passes through through the air it
essentially goes through mostly without
being absorbed and without being
scattered so that is one reason why air
is transparent and that's why we cannot
see it so absorption there's almost no
absorption of light scattering what
about scattering so air molecules do
scatter light but the scattering is
extremely weak what is the scattering
called it's called rally scattering r a
y l e i g rail scattering and you can't
notice it over here but you can notice
it if you look up into the sky in
daytime you will see the sky is blue why
is it blue it's because of rail
scattering so this phenomenon ra
scattering is responsible for the blue
color of the sky it's also responsible
for the yellowish reddish oranges color
of orangish color of the sky when the
Sun is setting far at the Horizon so up
there it's blue and at the Horizon when
when the Sun is setting or when it's
rising you will see the the sky is going
to be yellowish or redish reddish or
orangish so that is because of raay
scattering so light is scattered but
it's scattered very weakly but it's not
enough the scattering is not enough to
make air visible in the way that smoke
is visible or fog is visible so smoke
and fog they scatter way more light than
the actual molecules of of air itself so
the density of air is very low so
compared to a liquid okay you're talking
about liquids right so uh so when it
when it comes to liquids liquids are
much denser than than
water than air water is much denser than
air solid substances are much denser
than air so that's why they have
different phenomena they actually
do do become visible right so water is
visible because it has a much higher
density than air the water molecules are
packed closely together and that allows
water molecules to scatter and reflect
light much more strongly than air
molecules smoke is visible because it
has solid and liquid particles suspended
in air and these particles are dense and
they are numerous enough to scatter and
reflect light why is fire visible why is
fire visible fire is visible because of
incandescent particles and gases that
are part of the FL flame and they emit
light because of the extremely high
temperatures so these are the reasons
why fire and water and other substances
are visible but air is not visible we
obviously do feel the air one of the
reasons we feel air is because of the
air air pressure there's a tremendous
amount of pressure that the the
atmosphere of the planet exerts on us
you standing somewhere you're going to
have 100 kilometers of
air on top of your head so there going
to it's going to exert some pressure
right so there is air pressure and
moving air also exerts pressure on your
skin and it causes Sensations first of
all because of the pressure it causes
and also because of the temperature
change so these are the reasons why you
sense you can sense air you can sense
wind but you can't see it and that's why
air is more or less invisible except
when you see it up high in the sky when
there's a 100 plus kilometers of air
between you and uh and outer space and
you can see um you can see the color of
the air which is blue or it's yellowish
reddish in the evenings and early
mornings Summit statement says if humans
and present day Apes share a common
ancestry why don't Apes exhibit logical
thinking and develop like humans what
enabled humans to become
civilized well that's a good question so
we do we know that apes and humans share
a common ancestry the last common
ancestor of humans in chimpanzees I
think the split happened what two to
four million years before today roughly
and then there was a common ancestor of
humans chimpanzees and gorillas that
existed around roughly I think 8 million
years before today don't quote me on
that I could be off by a million or two
years but you get the point right we had
common
ancestors so why don't Apes exhibit the
same kind of thinking Etc that we
do it's because of we because we evolved
differently think about dogs and and and
bears you look at a dog's face you can
look at a bear's face quite similar
right they would at some point in time
have had uh common ancestors but they
have different levels of intelligence I
know bears are also very intelligent
they're almost like gigantic dogs but uh
let me give give a better example
consider the difference between between
a chimpanzee and a a lower monkey like a
slow lores or something significant
difference in in the level of
intelligence it's because each
species evolved separately and in
different ways in the past you did not
have air travel you know train travel
all that stuff so you could not travel
long distances it was very hard to
travel long distances on foot so when
populations got split off for whatever
reason they evolved for million millions
of years separately and wherever you
evolve there are different sets of
parameters different sets of climatic
and geographical conditions different
kinds of foods that's available and so
on and because of that the the species
evolve differently and acquire different
characteristics and I think it was
because of whatever accident of nature
that we evolved the way we did our
brains became much larger we became
mostly bipedal chimpan and gorillas can
still Crouch and you know walk on all
four we are exclusively bipedal
creatures and when you become bipedal
and you stand up on two feet then you
the your eyes are much higher from the
ground than for example that of a cat or
a dog I mean if you you know there are
videos on YouTube people some some
people attach GoPro cameras or small
cameras to the colors of cats and all
and then you can see the world from
their level and you can see how much
closer to the ground it is and how how
less information is accessible to the
eyes at that level but when you higher
up I mean think of it you go to the top
of a 100 100 story building and see how
far you can see and how much information
is available to your brain just through
your eyes so the higher you are the more
information is a available and the more
your brain needs to develop to be able
to process that information in real time
so because we became bipedal exclusively
bipedal our brains had to adapt to this
postural change and grow larger to be
able to absorb and process more
information much more information in
real time chimpanzees can walk on two
feet but they often walk on all fours
Etc right and so because of the
different ways in which we evolved we we
acquired different levels of
intellectual abilities and different
levels of
intelligence so I think what enabled
humans to become civilized first of all
we became more intelligent our brains
the size of our brain the volume of our
brainal capacity increased because of
our bipedal stature the bipedal posture
of ours and then because the brain had
expanded it had
become capable of absorbing and
processing more data more information we
also it also manifested itself in other
ways we became more social communicative
we developed language we developed
societies cooperation eventually
division of labor then we eventually
discovered fire and so and so forth so
these are the process by processes and
Agriculture and then civilization so
these are the processes by which we
became way more civilized than
apes and that's essentially how it is
that's that's all about
Evolution aded Guru Prasad says our
brain doesn't use mathematics still how
is it able to do a lot of essential
calculations right you know when we talk
about physics
our brains understand physics you know
you know you can you can solve Newton's
equations of motion for projectile
motion you throw a projectile you can
you know derive the equation for the
projectile motion it'll go in a
parabolic path and it will reach a
certain maximum height and then it will
it will once again fall at a certain
distance from which you threw it
depending on the angle and the speed of
the thing and the mass of the object you
can you you know calculate all of this
using Newton's equations and uh derive
the equations for parabolic motion and
you can solve that for the size of your
projectile the speed at which you throw
it the angle at which you throw uh
relative to Earth's surface Etc so you
can do it like that but when you play a
game when you play let's say whatever
Cricket whatever you throw a ball you
don't have to do any calculations you
just intuitively know how high the ball
will go and what where it it's going to
touch the ground and you can catch it
before it does that right so you just
know it
intuitively what about okay so we know
that intu intuitively because we got
massive brains compared to other animals
what about dogs you take a ball you
throw it your dog's gonna go after the
ball is going to know exactly where the
ball is going to touch the ground is
going to jump leap up into the air and
catch the ball midair before it touches
the ground how does a dog know this
physics how does did the dog solve
Newton's equations of motion
or or parabolic you know projectile
motion how did the dog know this and
when we walk on two feet we know exactly
what the balance of the balance of all
the forces is we are we are being acted
upon by multiple forces at any given
point in time the force of gravity and
the whatever the you know wind and and
and atmospheric pressure and so much
more and we are walking which is an
unstable movement but we are able to
balance it in real time without even
thinking about it and the same goes for
other animals how do we do it we are
performing calculations in real time are
we or are we not what is the deal so
this clearly a tremendous amount of
understanding that the brain has so how
does it happen is the question so look
when it comes to the human brain we have
about what's the number how many NE
neurons between 80 and 90 billion
neurons okay we have between 80 and 90
billion B
neurons that is one
with nine zeros after it and you
multiply that by 80 or 90 that's the
number of neurons you have in the brain
and these neurons are all interconnected
they con they communicate through
synapses and each neuron each individual
neuron can form thousands tens of
thousands of synaptic connections and
this creates an incredibly complicated
incredibly vast and complex network of
neurons and these neurons they
communicate with each other via
electrical impulses and chemical signals
neurotransmitters all that and this
neural activity this incredibly
complicated complex neural activity
allows for the rapid transmission and
processing of various kinds of
information so that is one way the brain
works that is kind of the way the brain
works the brain it doesn't it it
processes information in parallel it
doesn't do it sequentially when you have
a computer program a standard computer
program it it runs sequentially but in a
standard regular computer but when it
comes to the brain information is being
processed in parallel you have different
se you know uh area of the brain that
specialize in various kinds of
information and data and perception and
they are all communicating with each
other and processing information in
various part of of the brain in parallel
so multiple processes happen inside the
brain simultaneously so there's a very
efficient and very rapid handling of
sensory input also motor control
cognitive tasks throwing catching
walking speaking cognitive tasks motor
control the way we you know control our
Limbs and so on and then the brain it
excels at recognizing patterns it can
recognize shapes it can recognize faces
it can recognize sounds it can recognize
various other stimuli by comparing the
incoming sensory data okay the sound the
shape the phas it can compare that
incoming data
with stored representations of data
memories so memories are are are complex
packets of data you could say that are
stored in the brain and then the brain
has an an ability to reorganize itself
it's called neuroplasticity it
reorganizes itself simply by forming new
neural connections so this property
neuroplasticity allows the brain to
adapt to new information it allows the
brain to adapt to new experiences it
even allow the brain to recover from
injuries and give you a reasonably
similar lifestyle before and after let's
say some kind of injury on the brain
right so that's how the brain works and
through this learning you could call it
reinforcement learning experience Etc
the brain refines its processing
capabilities and reinforcement learning
in in in it uh involves practice
repetition and these these activities
they Str Len the various Pathways in the
in the brain neural Pathways which makes
the execution of various kinds of tasks
more efficient over time and
uh it can I suppose the brain can also
perform basic arithmetic computations
maybe intuitively it can quickly
estimate quantities and recognize
patterns and perform simple addition
subtractions probably without conscious
effort and so on and then the brain is
for more complex problems and operations
the brain is very much capable of uh
logical reasoning it's obviously this
memory retrieval this approximation when
you see a mountain compared to a stone
you immediately know that the mountain
is way more massive than a stone so you
know all of that logical reasoning
approximation is there and the brain
breaks down complex problems into
manageable parts and uses the strategies
it has learned over time to find
Solutions and this happens mostly
subconsciously it is said that only 1%
of the mind it is I don't know I don't
know how accurate that is but roughly 1%
of the mind is conscious 99% is uncon is
subconscious so the subconscious is
where all the processing happens without
us knowing about it and so on so that's
kind of how the brain
operates it doesn't use mathematics it
may use
um you know but it's still able to do
all these essential and very complicated
calculations in real time without us
even knowing that all of this is
happening we don't realize we don't we
don't cognitively sense the calculations
and all pattern recognition all that
happening it just
happens so our our conscious mind is
unaware of the subconscious processing
that's happening and that's the way the
brain is organized and that's how it
functions and we know actually next to
nothing about uh about how the brain
really functions but uh yeah over time
we understand more I
guess Malik said says everything around
us is made up of atoms and as we know
well as we know yes does it mean that
our brain and this means that our brain
is also made up of atoms and our brain
is able to think and it is conscious we
know that yes doesn't doesn't that tell
us that atoms can think even
neurochemical okay neurochemicals which
neurochemical processes that happen in
the brain and are sub atomically made up
of atoms is this argument correct to say
that atoms can think okay so we know the
brain is made up of atoms molecules and
further
complex substances like amino acids and
proteins and neurons and synapses and
all of that so there's a lot of
neurochemistry in there there's
chemistry there's biology and at the
fundamental deeper level there is
physics quantum physics at the end of at
the bottom of it all all of that and
obviously everything is made up of atoms
so we know that we are conscious and we
can think and we can perceive the world
and all all that so doesn't mean that
atoms can think that is the fundamental
question you're asking so think about it
like this what do I have here it's a
rock It's Made of atoms I have more
rocks I show you a White Rock there's a
blue Rock here there's
a blackish dark purple rock here there a
yellowish whitish Rock here these are
all rocks they are also made of atoms
they are actually crystals crystalline
objects they're also made of atoms why
don't they
think why don't they think why doesn't
my shirt collar think why doesn't my
microphone think why don't these books
think why doesn't that that wooden
rhinoceros behind me why doesn't he
think why doesn't that deer think you
know that that wooden deer and so on why
don't they think they're also made of
atoms so
clearly it tells you that this over here
the brain is a very special
configuration of
atoms nothing else in the universe is
capable of thinking or being conscious
brains are human brain cat brain monkey
brain be brain all have different levels
of consciousness but we know that
they're conscious and we know that
there's some thought going on in there
right so it's not atoms that think it is
very
special configurations of
atoms that seem to be the seat of
Consciousness and thinking how does it
work we don't know we don't know we
simply do not understand Consciousness
from a scientific perspective and from
any other perspective also we don't
understand I mean in philosophy
spirituality religion there are various
schools of thought as to how
Consciousness happens and all that
there's the concept of the Soul Etc but
we talking about science over here we're
talking science observable phenomena
physical object
only so from the perspective of
observable phenomena and physical object
only we only know that there's a brain
in here and it seems to be the seat of
Consciousness and the seat of
thought and we know that if somebody
gets brain injured or something the
Consciousness
disappears I mean if somebody
unfortunately gets shot in the head you
know Consciousness goes and and thoughts
go and life itself goes so clearly the
brain is is is the seat of Consciousness
and
thought it's made of atoms but there's
so many different configurations of
atoms and they don't think only the
brain thinks so it seems to be that a
very
special U configuration of atoms is the
cause for Consciousness and thinking or
maybe it is the seat of Consciousness
and thinking but how does it happen
where does Consciousness arise from is
it an emerging phenomenon is it a
different kind of phenomenon is it
something that permeates the Universe we
have absolutely no idea we don't even
have a physical scientific definition of
Consciousness we don't have that also we
don't even have that we don't even have
a definition in science whether it is
physics chemistry biology Neuroscience
whatever we don't have a definition of
Consciousness so we can't answer the
question right now the answer to your
question is beyond the reach of science
but it's a great question that you're
asking because it it it it helps you
understand conceptually what these
phenomena are because we have atoms
everywhere different configuration of
atom atoms rocks books statues objects
whatever they don't think why what is
special about this something about the
brain is special but what is it we don't
quite know and we're trying to figure it
out swapnil says how did the progression
from mathematics to physics to chemistry
to biology unfold in the universe
demonstrating a seamless Continuum so at
the beginning of it all as far as We
Know was the initial Singularity of the
universe the Big Bang Singularity or
near Singularity we don't quite know
whether it was a genuine Singularity or
near Singularity if you look at Loop
quantum gravity there's no Singularity
there's only uh the unit which is 10 ra
to minus 98 or something uh times the
plank scale I think plank plank length
uh so yeah plank length or or C or meter
I'm not sure but yeah it's extremely
extremely
small so we had let's say a big bang
Singularity and then something caused it
caused the universe to expand space time
to expand and initially you had a single
unified Force as far as the best we can
understand a single unified force in
which described everything in the
universe so the initial state of the
universe was
extremely dense extremely hot and you
had you had all kinds of energy and
particles everything in that hot dense
soup like you say in the
cliche so and and you had a single force
and then you as the universe expanded
and started cooling you had symmetry
breaking and the various forces emerged
out of this the broke off from the
unified Force whether it is gravity or
the electromagnetic force or the strong
nuclear force or the weak nuclear force
they all broke off they all separated at
different uh energy scales temperature
scales um and it all followed it all
obeyed the laws of physics which are
described by mathematics so think of it
like somebody out of the outside the
universe
coded wrote a big
program which
encodes the laws of the universe so the
program was written in the language of
mathematics essentially that's what you
that's how you can understand
mathematics mathematics describes the
regularities and patterns that underly
the
universe so that's mathematics and
that's how that that's what underlies
everything and then you had physics
which describes the actual
laws the actual objects and everything
that's inside the universe and then you
had expansion of the universe inflation
super luminal expansion and then as the
universe cooled down you had you know
the formation of the first atoms then
the formation of the first uh Stars Then
galaxies Dark Matter dark energy are
somewhere in there we don't know what
their actual role is but uh so the
universe was very very very very hot
initially and then it started expanding
and Cooling and the Stars Etc formed
galaxies eventually started forming and
there was a time in the universe's
ancient history when the average
temperature of the universe was the
average temperature that we have on
Earth today so it would have been very
easy for life to form anywhere in the
universe at the time so what you have is
your have mathematics you have physics
and
then through physics you have chemistry
because you have
molecules combining together in in
through processes that we call chemical
processes and the formation of various
complicated uh uh molecules like amino
acids which are the bases of proteins
and all so it all happened in the
systematic uh continuous manner logical
Manner and eventually you had life we
don't quite know how life happened but
it happened at at lower temperature
scales clearly I mean the kind of life
we understand there could be other forms
of life that we we're not aware of that
we can't perhaps even imagine perhaps
but the kind of life that we are
familiar with it would have emerged at
much lower temperature scales and how
did DNA DNA molecules come into
existence we don't quite know uh it's
possible the DNA molecules could have
first formed in the universe when the
universe the average temperature of the
entire universe was about the room temp
average room temperature on Earth today
possibly you know and then maybe they
drifted Across the Universe on on space
dust and and and space rocks Etc and the
seeded life in various parts of the
universe that's a
possibility but we have zero evidence of
that so it's just a hypothesis it's just
speculation but that's overall how it
would have happened and obviously
everything the underlying everything
thing you have the laws of physics which
are described by mathematics so the laws
of
biology are described the the the
foundation of biology we have the laws
of chemistry chemical reactions in
chemical reactions to understand that
you have to understand quantum physics
and all and various other forms other
fields of physics and underlying physics
you have mathematics so that's the
connection between
everything Asha Kash says what's dark
Dark Matter Dark Matter okay dark matter
is so first of all how did this idea how
did the idea of Dark Matter come about
it came about through observational
evidence uh in the early 20th century it
was discovered that the Milky Way was
not the only was not the universe we had
far away objects Way Beyond the Milky
Way Stars galaxies Etc mainly galaxies
and then it was discovered that the
galaxies are receding away from us they
moving further and further away from us
so there's red shift and all that that
we discovered and then we discovered
that when we observe
galaxies and we take spectrometric
spectrometric
measurements of the light coming from
the galaxies then you will find that one
end of the Galaxy let's say it's a
spiral galaxy one end of the Galaxy the
light coming from there will be red
shifted and one end will be blue shifted
so we know that galaxies are are
rotating and based on the red shift and
blue shift we can determine at what
speed the galaxies are
rotating and then you can calculate the
the amount of mass inside a Galaxy by
Computing its
Luminosity so we know how much mass is
in a galaxy we know at what speed it's
rotating and then you find that the
rotation of speed of the galaxies that
we observe it doesn't match the amount
of matter the Galaxy
contains it's it's rotating way faster
why is
that that can only be explained by by
by by saying that the galaxy has way
more mass but we can't see it and we
find that in most galaxies these are
called rotation curves we know we find
that galaxies rotate faster than they
should be rotating based on how much the
amount of matter we see so there is
clearly some kind of kind of unseen
matter inside these galaxies or or
that's part of the Galaxy but we can't
see it and that's how the idea the
concept of Dark Matter came into
existence so we now know that most
Galaxies have this
phenomenon and if we add everything up
we find that
U uh about 24% of the mass energy of the
universe roughly 24 25% is made of Dark
Matter only four or 5% is visible matter
everything we we see in the Universe
Stars galaxies nebula whatever dust
clouds everything everything that is
Luminous makes up only about 5% of the
mass energy of the universe about 25%
roughly give or take is dark matter and
about 70% is something called dark
energy which is even more mysterious but
anyhow that is what dark matter is and
there are lots of theories about what
Dark Matter could actually be it is
clearly some it could be some class of
particles there is modified neonian
Dynamics also MD which which which kind
of gives you a solution for this without
having to uh postulate or
theorize U that there are classes of
particles out there dark particles but
if you set aside MD you'll the theories
are that dark matter could be various
classes of particles either particles
that are purely gravitating in nature
purely gravitational they only interact
via gravity not via the electromagnetic
force or maybe
there could these particles could also
have the weak
interaction so there are lots of
different classes of particles that have
been proposed like wimps and machos and
Axion
and and strange let primordial black
holes stable quantized bound states of
pror black holes much more so that is
what we understand of dark matter we
have zero observational evidence thus
far of any of these particles there are
certain experiments that are running and
some experiments give you some telltale
signs of something out there but it is
still under dispute so we still don't
have any answers so that is essentially
what dark matter
is okay shakas once again says are worm
holes real or are they mere theories
look we have never
observed a wormhole a wormhole so worm
holes are a certain class of solutions
of the Einstein field equations of
general
relativity okay so you solve these
equations these field equations and one
of some of the solutions are Wormhole
Solutions so wormholes are essentially
shortcuts between two very far apart
regions of space time it's like you know
the the classical cliche is that you
take a sheet of paper bend it in two and
you poke a hole through that that's like
kind of an analogy for a wormhole so it
is a valid class of equations of the
Einstein Einstein field Rel equations of
general relativity but we have never
actually observed a wormhole so it's
it's so it is a theoretical
theoretically valid solution but it has
never been observed thus far but it's
possible that the objects we observe
some of them could be wormholes so we
know that at the heart at the center of
most galaxies you have super massive
black
holes we haven't actually gone there and
and measured the properties of the black
hole we have the Event Horizon telescope
that has taken snapshots of two black
holes one is the Sagitarius a star super
massive black hole at the center of our
galaxy and there's another one as well
much further away and we know that the
the snapshot that we get of the black
hole it actually matches exactly what
general relativity tells us but there
are black there are these super massive
objects at the centers of most galaxies
that we know of and it's possible it's
it's possible that some of those could
actually be worm holes but we don't
quite know
so we don't know for sure we don't have
an ambiguous observational evidence that
so and so object is actually a wormhole
not a black hole we don't know but they
could exist they could certainly very
much exist according to the laws of
physics according to general relativity
they should exist but we haven't
observed them yet so thus far they are
theoretical objects but someday we may
find them right
Rohan bidi says in relativity gravity is
a result of mass in the fabric of space
relativity also says that mass and
energy are two forms of the same thing
then does energy also generate gravity
your answer is sir yes energy does
indeed generate gravity according to
Einstein's theory of general relativity
and this is a profound and very
important Insight okay so we know the
wonderful Yul famous uh equation eal mc^
s equivalence of mass and energy it is
Einstein's famous equation which tells
us that mass and energy are equivalent
and
interchangeable okay so in general
relativity the presence of mass curves
SpaceTime and this curvature is what we
experience as
gravity now since mass and energy are
equivalent energy also curves SpaceTime
and generates a gravitational field and
this applies to all forms of energy like
the kinetic energy of moving objects
potential energy in fields
electromagnetic energy and even the
energy of the gravitational fields
themselves so the mathematical
formulation of general relativity so in
the mathematical formulation of general
relativity the source of gravity is
described by the stress energy tensor
and this stress energy tensor includes
contributions from Mass as well as
energy so the answer is yes so in most
most uh let's say everyday situations
the gravitational effect of energy is
negligible compared to that of mass but
it does become significant in extreme
asymptotic scenarios like for example
the conditions that we had in the early
Universe when energy densities were
extremely high so there you would
actually noticeably see this then when
it comes to black holes where the
curvature of space time is Extreme and
when it comes to the large scale
structure of the universe where the
energy that is dark energy plays a
crucial role so yes uh I agree that that
that mass and energy are the are two
forms of the same thing and energy does
indeed let's say like you say generate
gravity right it it does actually
contribute to gravity what we what we
perceive is gravity
potato
praiser says what will happen if Strange
Matter comes into contact with a black
hole will the black hole turn into
Strange Matter all right that is a
complicated question let's understand uh
what Strange Matter is what is Strange
Matter so to understand
that
um how do I approach this okay you may
have you may have heard of stars going
Supernova stars explode right and that
is caused by the collapse of a star upon
itself and then there's process that
also leads to an explosion now depending
on the mass of the star the object that
is the resultant that results from this
incredible force of the Stars collapse
upon itself upon its core the object
could either be a neutron star or a
black hole depending on on whether the
internal components of the matter are
able to resist give an outward push
successfully to the imploding matter or
whether they simply can't resist that so
you going to either have a a black hole
or a neutron star so if the star is more
massive you'll have a black hole
otherwise you will have a neutron star a
neutron star is essentially a gigantic
city-sized Atomic nucleus with protons
and neutrons inside it lots of protons
and neutrons squash together so it has
the it has the size of a city let's
say roughly 10 km or something diameter
but it has the mass of an entire star
tremendous gravity so it's a gigantic
Atomic nucleus and inside it you have
protons and neutrons now protons and
neutrons they are made up of something
called quarks quarks are fundamental
subatomic particles fundamental
particles and you have six kind of
quarks up down
strange charm top bottom six different
kinds of quarks and the matter that we
are familiar with it is it is only made
it is only composed of two different
kinds of quarks up and down quarks so
protons are U two up quarks and one down
quark and neutrons are UDD one up quark
and two down quarks triplets and quarks
have something called confinement
they're confined together and you no
matter what you do they will always
stick together you will never find free
quarks
anywhere and this color confinement it's
the it's called color color confinement
and if you try to break two two quarks
or three quarks apart you have to give
tremendous amounts of energy and that
energy will be used to generate more
quarks which again stick together so
that's what you have now it is possible
that
inside neutron stars where the where the
density and pressure are incredible you
may have deconfinement which means that
the protons and neutrons dissolve into
their individual component quarks which
swim around freely because the
environment inside the neutron star is
so incredibly dense and the pressure is
so incredibly high so you may have
deconfinement inside neutron star okay
I'm coming to Quark matter I'm I'm
coming to that I'm coming to Strange
Matter so I said I said there are six
kinds of quarks up down top bottom
strange
charm now it is
possible and and the two St
forms of quarks kinds of quarks are up
and down the other ones they they
Decay now it's possible that inside a
neutron star where you have Quark matter
deconfined Quark matter because of the
pressure and various conditions you may
have S some quarks getting converted
into strange
quarks and strange quarks have very
strange
properties and uh they could you know
combine with other
quarks and
they could form extremely stable matter
maybe the most stable matter that exists
anywhere in the universe and they could
possibly convert other quarks into more
strange quarks but generally so so that
is strange matter which is a combination
of the standard quarks with a strange
Quark um so that is what Strange Matter
is but that obviously is matter that
would be at the heart that would be
inside confined inside a neutron star
from outside the neutron star looks just
like a standard neutron star we don't
know what's inside inside there could be
Strange Matter strange Quark matter now
when Could This Strange
Matter be you know be exposed to the
universe so when you have neutron star
collisions which are incredibly
energetic phenomena that's when the in
insides of neutron stars are spewed out
into the universe when you have the
Collision of two neutron stars they
spiral around each other there's an
inspiral and they eventually Collide so
that is one way where Quark strange
Quark matter could be ejected into the
universe the other phenomenon is the
collision between a neutron star and a
black hole which also
could result in some part of the neutron
star being ejected out into space and
the rest would be absorbed by the black
hole so in that case you would have
Strange Matter traveling across the
universe in Strange Matter droplets
called
strangelets so that is strange matter
okay that's strange matter it it is it
has strange quarks and it
is theorized to be extremely stable the
most stable matter that you can have in
the
universe and if Strange Matter comes
into contact with regular matter or
ordinary matter it it could turn your
ordinary matter into Strange Matter so
if a strange light a droplet of Strange
Matter would would hit the earth it
could turn the earth into Strange Matter
and all life would disappear we would
all become strange it could if a if a
droplet of Strange Matter were to hit
the sun it could turn the the sun into a
strange
star the entire matter of the sun could
become strange okay and what happens to
a black hole if Strange Matter comes
into contact with the black hole well
I'll tell you something about black
holes a black hole the properties of a
black hole are described by only three
quantities Mass charge angular momentum
mass m charge Q angular momentum L those
are the only three properties that a
black hole that can describe a black
hole nothing else so it doesn't matter
what goes inside a black hole strange
quarks or standard quarks or whatever it
doesn't matter it makes no difference so
a black hole will want will not become a
strange black hole it will just become a
larger black hole it will swallow The
Strange Matter it'll become a larger
black hole that's it it will not turn
into Strange Matter it will remain a
black hole the only change could be to
its mass charge or angular momentum
depending on how The infalling Strange
Matter entered the black hole that's it
nothing
else all right Asha kashia says why are
all the planets in our solar system
round in shape while comets and
meteorites are kind of uneven so I'm
sure I've answered this question before
but let's take it again there is a
phenomenon called hydrostatic
equilibrium so what happens is that when
you have a large enough object with
large enough Mass then the gravitational
force of the object that the that that
it exerts upon its constituent Parts it
becomes stronger the gravity of the of
the object becomes stronger than the
structural strength of the materials
that make it up that are part of it so
that's how the object becomes spherical
because the most you know the the most
perfect shape that you can have of any
object is a sphere so the gravitational
force of the object it it defeats the
structural strength of of its of its con
constituents which is the rocks and
whatever else that you have in the in
the object and that's how it becomes it
becomes kind of spherical so a sphere
essentially like I said before in a
different answer it has the smallest
surface area for a given volume and the
lowest energy State and nature wants the
lowest energy State you can think of it
that way and that's how planets become
spherical once they acquire a certain
Mass so it's about hydrostatic
equilibrium but when it comes to objects
like asteroids and meteorites and
meteors and comets Etc these are are too
small for the gravity of that object to
defeat the internal strength of the
material The Rock and whatever else it
else it is uh and it's also the fact the
fact is that these objects are left over
from the initial stage the initial uh
era which was the birth of the solar
system and uh and maybe these objects
they never were able to come together
and and coal together which would form
planets so that's why uh these smaller
objects are not spherical in shape while
while the larger planets themselves are
spherical in
shape y Noka says do you have doubts
about whether you are a boltzman
brain a boltzman brain is a philos
philosophical concept it's a concept
that's not well it's related to
statistical ma mechanics
Etc so the concept of a boltzman brain
essentially is it says that
uh a boltzman brain is a disembodied
brain it's it's a hypothetical
self-aware entity that spontaneously
arises because of random fluctuations in
the universe o in a vast Universe over
an immensely long time scale so in an
enormously vast Universe with immensely
long time scales random
fluctuations could spontaneously create
an incredibly complex structure
including something as complicated as
intricate as a brain with
self-awareness and uh memories of a life
that it has lived which it actually has
not it Just spontaneously arose because
of random fluctuations so uh statistical
mechanics tells us that if you give if
you have enough
time given enough time and given every
possible state of matter no matter how
improbable every any possible state of
matter could emerge in the universe
given enough time so it's the
probability of something like this
happening is extremely extremely low but
not zero it is a nonzero probability so
over an almost infinite time scale
a brain you know a fully functional
disembodied brain with false memories of
having had entire life could actually
appear spontaneously so that is the
concept of a boltman brain it's a
philosophical concept and that kind
of yeah it it raises various kinds of
questions about existence and so on but
I've never had doubts about whether I'm
a balsman brain I've never thought that
deeply but yes it's an intriguing
question and possibility
okay with that I'm at the end of the
questions that I've taken from the
comments now if you have some questions
in the live chat go ahead and I will
take a
few and let's try okay let's try and
take questions that I have not taken
before but uh that would be difficult to
find I'm
sure sh vatsa says if white dwarves turn
into black dwarfs what will neutron
stars turn into
H so what's the so white dwarfs will
eventually turn into black dwars a white
dwarf is essentially what's left over
from the death of a small star like the
Sun so the sun our sun will not go
supernova it's too small to go supernova
it'll simply eject it will eventually in
about five billion years from today
become a red red giant red super giant
red giant and then it will eject its
external layers and into what's called a
planet 30 nebula or something and at the
core will be left what is called a white
dwarf which is a gigantic carbon Crystal
extremely hot incandescent carbon
Crystal a gigantic diamond
essentially and over billions and
billions of years it will lose its heat
and eventually turn into a black dwarf
that will happen over I don't know
billions or maybe trillions of years so
that's event that's the eventual state
that the fate of the Sun a black dwarf
first a white dwarf then after an
immensely long period of time a black
dwarf what will neutron stars turn into
that's a fascinating question so neutron
stars what could they turn into I think
they will remain Atomic nuclei they may
lose their heat but they will REM remain
gigantic macroscopic Atomic nuclei as
long as there is no collision with other
neutron stars or or other objects or
black holes they will simply continue to
exist they don't Decay they don't
evaporate they stay what they are they
may lose their heat over incredibly long
time scales but I don't see neutron
stars turning into something else they
will remain Atomic nuclei interesting
question
interesting
um suil Matra says what's quantum
entanglement quantum entanglement is a
very strange Quantum property U
essentially what happens is that look
um every Quantum object whether it's an
electron or a proton or whatever it is
described by a wave
function a wave function is a
mathematical object that describes the
probability of it existing at various
points in time at given loc at various
locations in the universe that's the
wave function of a particle okay now
there are certain sometimes you what
happens is that you have entangled
particles which means that these two
part particles are described by a single
wave function so they are entangled they
cannot be described by two separate wave
functions they can only be described by
a single wave function and that means
that they are entangled what does that
mean it means that if You observe one
particle you will immediately know the
state of the other particle the
corresponding particle instantaneously
no matter where it is even if it is 100
light years away you will
instantaneously know it what the state
of the other particle is of the other
entangled particle so it's like having a
pair of gloves a left-handed glove and
right-handed glove you put them into two
separate boxes you shift one off to
Moscow you shift the other off to
Washington your friend in Washington
opens it he finds he or she finds a
right-handed glove or she will
immediately know that your friend in
Moscow has received a left-handed love
that sort of thing that's a very rough
analogy that describes the entanglement
phenomenon but you know it's not exactly
like that and um there is no
transmission of information in
entanglement contrary to what some
science fiction uh TV shows show for you
but that's essentially what quantum
entanglement
is
um VV says is time a mind construct as
we experience past future only in now
look time is one of the biggest
mysteries in in science in physics okay
and we don't know what time is is time
something that emerges do do we have
atoms and molecules of time is is it an
emerging property of the universe is it
something that's external to the
universe I mean if you look at quantum
mechanics time is an external parameter
okay time is an external classical
parameter in quantum mechanics it's not
something that emerges out of quantum
theory so we don't know what time is and
we perceive it only vaguely very hazily
and yeah our actual perception of the
world is what's happening right now but
it's because of Consciousness that we
have memories and that's how we can
travel into our memories and even
speculate about future time scales but
what's happening is right now so we
don't know what time is is it a
construct of the Mind does it emerge
does it is it is it a consequence of
quantum entanglement and decoherence we
don't know we don't know we don't have
answers to this question it's a it's a
fundamental profound mystery in physics
in science and we don't have the answer
but that's why it's so fascinating
that's why physics is so fascinating
because we don't have answers to such
profound
questions um D Kat says there are
reports that Dyson's fears or forms may
have been discovered around stars in
outer space what are your thoughts
what's the likelihood that these alien
civilizations know us okay let's
understand what's been discovered
there's been a recent paper reasonably
recently in the monthly notices of the
Royal Astronomical Society mnras which
is a good Journal so a paper has been
published there and what they were
looking for so what's a Dyson spere
Sphere first of all a Dyson Sphere is
this
hypothetical gigantic engineering
construction which have in which you
have these panels that envelop a star
completely so that you can you can you
can absorb you can trap all of its
energy and use it for whatever you want
to use it so you would need to be a
hyper intelligent so civilization with
super human engineering capabilities to
be able to construct that that that
structure that can completely envelop a
star okay and then you can you can use
all the energy of the star then you then
you can use all the energy of the star
you know uh it's at your disposal that's
what a Dyson Sphere is it
is a feat of super
engineering which we simply aren't
capable of right now now what if there
are other there are civilizations out
there alien civilizations that have
constructed Dyson fears then what would
that look like from here that's the
question that scientists would ask
themselves astronomers astrophysicist
would ask them themselves and the answer
is if you have a star that's enveloped
completely in this structure Dyson
structure Dyson Sphere then that
structure will get hot it will
emit infrared light this glow of heat
heat glow which is infrared light so
what about we look for
that what about we look for that we know
what the characteristics of the glow are
like and we don't need to build new
instruments in telescopes to look for it
we have tremendous amounts of data we
that we already have at our disposal
from all the experiments we've done in
the past we have data for billions of
stars so why not just go through all the
data and search for that that those
signatures so that's what the the this
study did and I think they came up with
a number of dozen or two dozen or so
candidates for Dyson feares so it
doesn't tell you that these are genuine
Dyson spheres but they are showing the
characteristics that you would expect a
Dyson Sphere uh enclosed star to
exhibit but it there are other you know
possibilities you know other possible
explanations that could for for for the
same phenomenon just a you know a gas
cloud that's very hot for whatever
reason there there are so many other
ways by which you could explain what you
are observing here so it is not
definitive evidence of Dyson spheres but
it's an interesting study who knows some
of those may actually be Dyson spheres
so my thoughts are that we have to be
skeptical we have to be careful in
science you don't jump to conclusions
you have to look at all possible
explanations and first take those
explanations seriously that are more
plausible like a gas cloud that is hot
or whatever else the least likely
possibility is an alien civilization
with the Dyson
spere so that's how I see it uh but in
Cas in in in case some of these are
actual alien civilizations that have
constructed Dyson fears that would
indicate that are
incredibly way more advanced than what
we are today and I don't know if they
know us I hope they
don't I hope they don't
sir okay let's take maybe one or two
questions
um one or two more
questions what else what else what else
do we
have om beerer says in the movie
Interstellar Cooper the protagonist
sends coordinates to the Past through
the tesser ACT does this violate the law
of causality or is it a predefined loop
what happens when he goes there for the
first time um what happens in so the
Tesseract the Tesseract is something he
encounters inside a black hole right he
he jumps into a black hole and inside
the black hole he crosses the Event
Horizon there is a t Tess act apparently
in there and he sends coordinates back
to the past through the tser ACT does
this violate the law of Co it it does
violate the law of
causality it it could violate the law of
causality
so until you can deter you can determine
the problem exactly you don't even know
whether it's a whether it's a causal
lope or whether it is violating the law
of causality but when you do things like
going back in time and all you do end up
violating causality and that raises the
question as to whether causality is one
of the laws of the universe as far as we
know everything has a cause every effect
is a
cause um so is the universe causal in
nature or even quantum mechanics does
seem to sometimes violate causality so
yeah we're not sure if the if the the
universe is local if it is causal and
all
that but uh when you send information
back in time you do time travel all that
you do end up violating causality so
that's what I would
say okay let's take one more question
before we
end kenat says your all-time favorite
physicists and mathematicians
um
mathematicians
Oiler ramanujan
Jai uh perilman Gregory perilman so many
more so many more um physicists
obviously you would have to say Einstein
Neil B without Neil B he would not have
quantum mechanics he was one of the
Giants on Whose shoulders We Stand today
so definitely nil B Heisenberg
schinger um Oppenheimer why
not uh Sudan George Sudan great great
guy who should have won three Nobel
prizes three Nobel prizes you should
have won then you have Chandra shakar
obviously um Hawking sure L Lev
Lando and so on yeah a few just of you
obviously fainman obviously po Wolf Gang
po I'm sure if I think a little bit more
I I'll I can think of many more
anyhow um yeah let's let's end this
session with that question we have
crossed two hours once again so yeah
that's the end of today's session I
apologize to those of you whose
questions I'm not able to answer I can
see so many more but I'm going to end it
over here but we're going to keep doing
this so you can keep asking questions
and we'll take as many as possible all
right so thank you so much and I will
see you in the next live stream which
will be tomorrow and it's a totally
different topic it's history geopolitics
and current affairs so hope to see you
there if not in the next week's science
live stream so take care and I'll see
you soon and keep raising your standards
keep asking questions see you soon bye